<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Videocall Engineering - thoughts</title>
    <subtitle>Videocall Engineering</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://engineering.videocall.rs/tags/thoughts/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://engineering.videocall.rs"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://engineering.videocall.rs/tags/thoughts/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Why do &#x27;we&#x27; create art?</title>
        <published>2025-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/whyart/"/>
        <id>https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/whyart/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/whyart/">&lt;p&gt;From my inner perspective, art is a way to satisfy the inherent urge to experiment. I eventually discovered that engaging in art means simply “experimenting”—testing a hypothesis: &quot;Will this color evoke satisfaction?&quot;, &quot;Can this formula generate a more intriguing pattern?&quot;, &quot;Might this technique better express the idea that enlivens my mind?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a shader programmer, I work within a fully experimental process. Every line of code is an experiment. If you enjoy the thrill of experimentation, you likely share a passion for the intersection of art and math.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, each of these questions represents an experiment with no room for deceit, as you are the only impartial judge. In this way, the reliability of your creative process can even surpass conventional scientific knowledge.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a deeper level, what we often call &quot;aesthetic&quot; in art—seemingly subjective and random—reveals an essence that closely mirrors scientific inquiry. Whether it’s the dawn of art or the invention of the wheel, the underlying purpose is the same: to experience that indescribable satisfaction of making an experiment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>5 main root causes of psychological disorders</title>
        <published>2023-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/disorders/"/>
        <id>https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/disorders/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/disorders/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-causes-of-psychiatric-illness&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt;5 Causes of Psychiatric Illness&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt;Existence of Society&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Society provides the framework against which behavior is judged, allowing us to label actions as normal or abnormal. Without a community to compare against, it becomes challenging to define deviations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt;Existence of Culture&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Culture, with its own set of rules and traditions, shapes our understanding of mental health and acceptable behavior. Deviations from these norms can lead to an increase in psychiatric diagnoses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt;Mathematical Concept of &quot;Normality&quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Normality is inherently statistical, requiring a baseline to identify deviations as abnormal. This concept underpins how psychiatric disorders are classified as variations from societal norms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt;Existence of an Educational System&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Structured academic environments often uncover conditions like ADHD through systematic evaluation. In settings without formal testing, such conditions might not be recognized at all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt;Presence of High-Level Intelligence and Cognition&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Advanced cognitive abilities can sometimes be accompanied by psychological challenges, with schizophrenia being an extreme example. This may be seen as a genetic side effect of heightened intelligence and creativity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
