<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Videocall Engineering - face</title>
    <subtitle>Videocall Engineering</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://engineering.videocall.rs/tags/face/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://engineering.videocall.rs"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2023-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://engineering.videocall.rs/tags/face/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Gabor Patches on the Texture!</title>
        <published>2023-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/imgabor/"/>
        <id>https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/imgabor/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/imgabor/">&lt;p&gt;Below is a video featuring the outcome of my experiment. Take a close look and tell me, do you perceive the face in the image more in the horizontal or vertical orientation of the Gabor patches?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-media-max-width=&quot;560&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;with different orientations of Gabors... Actually interesting, because this reminds me of research underscoring the important role of horizontal info in face perception, revealing its crucial impact on facial encoding&#x2F;processing while vertical info often reduces these effects. 🙂 &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;t.co&#x2F;mUcCwJ4SBc&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;t.co&#x2F;mUcCwJ4SBc&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;t.co&#x2F;ghXyMWS7CO&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com&#x2F;ghXyMWS7CO&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&amp;mdash; enes altun (@emportent) &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;emportent&#x2F;status&#x2F;1713689728195690576?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 15, 2023&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;platform.twitter.com&#x2F;widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;script&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;ve been following my previous posts, you&#x27;re already familiar with the concept of Gabor patches and how they&#x27;re a fantastic tool for understanding various aspects of visual perception. What&#x27;s particularly intriguing is how these patches can alter our perception of orientation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;findings of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov&#x2F;19757911&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dakin and Watt (2009)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and others(there are a lot of papers about that issue), our perception of faces is significantly influenced by horizontal information compared to vertical. Some call this as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;royalsocietypublishing.org&#x2F;doi&#x2F;10.1098&#x2F;rspb.2023.1118#:~:text=The%20radial%20bias%20may%20modulate,the%20individual%20differences%20we%20observe.&quot;&gt;radial bias&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on this intriguing concept, Dakin and Watt&#x27;s study delves even deeper into our visual system&#x27;s preference for horizontal features in faces. They introduced the idea of facial &#x27;bar codes,&#x27; unique clusters of horizontal lines, akin to commercial bar codes, that our brains use for quick and efficient face recognition. This theory elegantly explains why we&#x27;re so adept at recognizing faces under various conditions and why certain transformations, like inverting a face, make recognition remarkably challenging. It&#x27;s a compelling reminder of how our visual system has fine-tuned itself over millennia, optimizing certain perceptual shortcuts for survival.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, when the Gabor patches are aligned horizontally, we&#x27;re likely to perceive the face more clearly. This phenomenon ties back to how our brains process faces, giving preferential treatment to horizontal features. It&#x27;s all about how the human visual system has evolved to prioritize certain spatial frequencies and orientations, especially when it comes to recognizing faces - one of the most crucial visual tasks we perform.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hey, don&#x27;t just take my word for it! Dive into the research, play around with the code, and explore the captivating realm of Gabor patches and visual perception. Who knows what other secrets are waiting to be uncovered?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: This code is computationally intensive, so only run it if you&#x27;re confident in your GPU&#x27;s capabilities. Also, please be cautious when adjusting the numbers—small changes can have big impacts!&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.shadertoy.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;Dd3fRB?gui=true&amp;t=10&amp;paused=true&amp;muted=false&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>My thesis in TLDR</title>
        <published>2023-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/thesis/"/>
        <id>https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/thesis/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://engineering.videocall.rs/posts/thesis/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-which-stage-we-perceive-differently-when-we-classified-faces&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt;On which stage we perceive differently when we classified faces?&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started reading about face perception, I found many studies. Most of these studies say that people see faces from their own race or species differently than others. But none of these studies answered my main question: At what point do we actually start to see these faces differently?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When does this happen? Right when the light hits our retinas? Or maybe a bit later, when the signals reach the occipital lobe at the back of our brains? Or is it even later, when our brain&#x27;s &quot;face recognition software&quot; kicks in?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;clarifying-the-term-race-in-my-research&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; Clarifying the Term &#x27;Race&#x27; in My Research &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my thesis, I use the term &quot;Race&quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to make it clear that I don&#x27;t see &quot;race&quot; as a biological concept, and I&#x27;m not approaching this from a &quot;racial&quot; perspective. Instead, I borrowed the term from scientific studies that discuss the &quot;other-race effect in face perception.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In simpler words, when I say &quot;Race&quot; in my research, I&#x27;m talking about faces that you don&#x27;t usually see in your day-to-day life. For example, in my experiments conducted in Antalya, I used &quot;Asian&quot; faces as the &quot;other&quot; category. Why? Because there aren&#x27;t many Asian people in Antalya, so these faces would be less &quot;familiar&quot; to the participants.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-i-tried-to-answer-this-question&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; How I tried to answer this question? &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of vision science, the visual hierarchy theory is a cornerstone. It tells us that there are three main stages when our brain classifies what we see:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Superordinate Level: Is it alive or not?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic Level: What kind of thing is it? (e.g., a dog)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subordinate Level: What specific type is it? (e.g., a pitbull)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov&#x2F;25208739&#x2F;&quot;&gt;research&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has shown that our brain can spot an animal in just 120 milliseconds but takes a bit longer to figure out it&#x27;s a dog. This quick initial categorization happens at the Basic Level, which aligns perfectly with the focus of my experiments.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you see a pitbull, your brain first decides it&#x27;s a living thing, then identifies it as a dog, and finally as a pitbull. Given this, I chose to zoom in on the &quot;Basic Level&quot; for my experiments. Participants were asked a simple question: &quot;If you see a face, click on X; if you don&#x27;t see a face, click on Y.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering, &quot;Why did I choose to focus on the &#x27;Basic Level&#x27; and not go deeper into the &#x27;Subordinate Level&#x27;?&quot; The answer lies in my interest in low-level visual properties. By keeping the research at the Basic Level, I could delve into the nitty-gritty of early visual processing without getting entangled in the complexities that come with higher-level categorizations like gender or specific facial features.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, a glance at the current ERP-face literature reveals that many studies are already exploring questions like &quot;What gender is this face?&quot; or &quot;Is this face familiar?&quot;, even some attentional oddbal tasks... These questions often require processing at the Subordinate Level, which involves more complex and high-level facial features. My aim was to strip away these complexities and get down to the basics—literally. This approach allowed me to isolate and study the fundamental visual cues that our brains use for face perception, making the research as low-level as possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-thats-not-enough&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; But thats not enough... &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could be answer my question partly but I wanted to know more. So I decided to use &quot;Spatial Frequency&quot;, more precisely &quot;Coarse-to-Fine&quot; theory in human vision. According to this theory, when we see an object in the world, we first perceive it&#x27;s coarse features (low spatial frequency) and then
fine features (high spatial frequency) so in the brain a fast-forward mechanism works like this: coarse features -&amp;gt; fine features -&amp;gt; classification.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See bellow image for more details:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;sf.png&quot; alt=&quot;SF&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How brain process a visual object&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;so-what-i-did&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; So what I did? &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armed with Python code and some nifty image processing techniques like Fourier Transform, RMSE, and luminance normalization, I set out to explore Spatial Frequencies (SFs). I designed my experiment using E-Prime software. A big shoutout to my awesome colleagues Nurullah, Furkan, and Semih for their invaluable help! Together, we conducted the experiment in our lab and managed to gather data from 30 participants using EEG, all within two weeks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-i-analyzed&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; What I analyzed? &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dived deep into the Event-Related Potentials (ERPs) for each participant. Specifically, I looked at:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P100&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Important for early visual processing&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N170&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Crucial for face perception&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N250&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Relevant for recognizing familiar faces&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-tools-which-electrodes-did-i-use&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; The Tools: Which Electrodes Did I Use? &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the EEG recordings, I used a variety of electrodes but focused my reporting on those placed on the occipital lobe, which is the brain&#x27;s visual processing center. The electrodes I reported are:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O1 and O2&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Standard occipital electrodes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PO3 and PO4&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Parieto-occipital electrodes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PO7 and PO8&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Additional parieto-occipital electrodes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-found-the-key-takeaways&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; What I Found: The Key Takeaways&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discovered quite a bit through my research, but I&#x27;ve focused on reporting the most crucial findings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Other-Race Effect in Early Stages&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: While I did find some significant results in the N250 ERP (especially in the PO electrodes), there were no significant differences in the P100 and N170 ERPs between Asian and Caucasian faces. This suggests that, at least in the early stages of visual processing, we don&#x27;t perceive faces of different races differently.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Species Differences in Higher Frequencies&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Interestingly, faces of other species didn&#x27;t differ from human faces in the low spatial frequency domain. However, we do perceive them differently in the high spatial frequency (HSF) or broadband, especially in the P100 ERP. This difference becomes even more distinct in the N170 and N250 ERPs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thesis is still under review, but I&#x27;ve conducted many detailed analyses and learned a lot. You can find the published version of my thesis &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tandfonline.com&#x2F;doi&#x2F;full&#x2F;10.1080&#x2F;13506285.2024.2415721#abstract&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Due to the length of the paper, I didn&#x27;t include the N250 results in the pre-print version. Rest assured, they are thoroughly reported in my full thesis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;softwares-and-tools-i-used&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; Softwares and Tools I Used&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;open-source-contributions&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; Open-Source Contributions&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love open-source and have contributed some tools that I wrote myself:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;altunenes&#x2F;easylab&quot;&gt;EasyLab&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: I created a Python GUI as a gift to my lab! It&#x27;s perfect for resizing images, renaming them with a prefix for easy reading in E-Prime 3.0, and even processing Spatial Frequencies using Fourier and Butterworth filters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;altunenes&#x2F;scramblery&quot;&gt;Scramblery&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: This tool is for scrambling images. I used scrambled images as a control condition in my research. It&#x27;s open-source, and there&#x27;s even a cool JavaScript version that runs online!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it out here: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;altunenes.github.io&#x2F;scramblery&#x2F;scramblerydemo.html&quot;&gt;Demo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;altunenes&#x2F;butter2d&quot;&gt;butter2d&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Rust implementation for Butterworth filter.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;proprietary-software&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; Proprietary Software&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BrainVision&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: I used this for my EEG recordings and initial data filtering. Unfortunately, it&#x27;s not open-source.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E-Prime 3.0&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: I used this for my experiment design. It&#x27;s buggy and makes you want to pull your hair out, but it&#x27;s the best option out there for designing experiments. It&#x27;s also not open-source. Made me think about creating an open-source alternative in the future using Rust while I was using it. Maybe one day!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;data-analysis&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; Data Analysis&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: After collecting the data, I did all my analyses using R. You can check out my workflow in this &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gist.github.com&#x2F;altunenes&#x2F;7081d34140335dd7764a92a7bfd12f1d&quot;&gt;gist file&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-fuel-coffee-music-and-friends&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:orange;&quot;&gt; The Fuel: Coffee, Music and Friends&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coffee&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Consumed in large quantities. I wasn&#x27;t picky about the brand.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Candlemass kept me company during those long hours of research. I dig into the doom.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friends&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: I couln&#x27;t have done it without my friends. They were both my emotional and technical support. Thank you Nurullah, Furkan and Semih! I&#x27;m forever grateful for your help. &amp;lt;3
Friendship in the lab is the best thing ever. I&#x27;m so lucky to have you guys!&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;paper-link&quot;&gt;Paper Link&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the more boring parts on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tandfonline.com&#x2F;doi&#x2F;full&#x2F;10.1080&#x2F;13506285.2024.2415721#abstract&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
